Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Madam.
What's going on, Jade?
You almost knocked into me.
Nothing.
I didn't listen to Consort Fleur on An Bihuai's case.
She's been having a tantrum for a few days.
I have to do something to soothe her.
I treat you differently from everyone else.
You know that.
Your Majesty, I dare not think that way.
It's just that I still dread to think about
what Yu and Concubine Beauté did.
I understand your apprehension.
I had the intention to promote you to Concubine.
But the duration of your service is relatively short,
and your promotion to Noble Lady before any service
was already an exception to the ancestors' rules.
I'm afraid you'll have to settle for this at the moment.
You'll have a rightful promotion when you're pregnant.
Huan Huan cares nothing about her rank.
As long as you have me in your heart, Si Lang.
I always do. How can I not?
I hold you very dear to my heart.
I have so many concubines in the harem and they don't bring me peace.
I can only feel calm when I'm with you here.
Huan Huan understands.
Your Majesty visited Meizhuang.
Does she have a better appetite now?
She's still the same, craving sour food.
[Sour food was believed to help with getting a boy.]
When will you have a big chubby boy of our own?
Why does it have to be a boy? Why not a girl?
I'll love our child just the same.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Peace to Lady Sourire.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Lingrong, where are you heading to?
I'm going to see Meizhuang.
What a coincidence!
His Majesty is going with me too.
- Let's go together.
- Yes.
Let's go.
Lady Vertu, you look very well.
I believe you'll give birth to a healthy child.
His Majesty the Emperor.
May peace be with Your Majesty.
What a coincidence! Everyone is here today.
Lady Vertu is pregnant.
As head of the harem, I must fulfill my duty
and provide the best care for her.
We follow Her Majesty.
Rise, rise.
Here, sit down.
How are you? How are you feeling today?
I'm feeling very well. I thank Your Majesty.
Has Your Majesty had dinner yet?
I have a new cook in my palace.
He cooks the best Jiangnan cuisine.
I had dinner at the Verdant Reading Hall
I believe Lady Sourire must have a good cook as well
to keep Your Majesty for dinner.
His Majesty always remembers the
ejiao longan soup at Your Highness's palace.
[from the night when Meizhuang almost drowned]
Now that Your Highness has another good cook,
His Majesty will yearn for Your Highness even in his dreams.
It's been over a month since we last spoke.
As always, Lady Sourire has a way with words.
This young lady has a sharp tongue.
Are you going to wage a war of words with her?
Your Majesty, I like Lady Sourire's sharp wit.
I always like to banter with her.
Your Majesty, the General of Ili has offered tributary cantaloupe.
Please have some with us.
Of course.
Your Majesty, it's time to select a name tag.
There's no need. I'll visit the Empress.
If you have cantaloupe at your palace, I'll eat with you later.
Yes.
Lady Sourire, spend some time with Lady Vertu.
Who's creeping around over there?
- We saw you!
- Come here!
Don't seize me! Don't seize me!
I'm Lady Vertu's maid.
This... Isn't this Poria, Lady Shen's maid?
Why were you sneaking about?
What are you carrying?
What is it?
Huh?
Were you trying to steal away with Lady Vertu's belongings?
What a disgraceful servant! Drag her out and...
Eh...
You're pregnant. Don't worry yourself about it.
My Lady... Save me, My Lady!
How do you expect me to tolerate you?
Aiya, get out of my sight!
Hold on.
This...
What... what is this?
Blood...
Why is there blood on these pants?
Could it be... a rob-and-murder?
That is strange.
Why would you steal nothing valuable
but some filthy clothes?
Are these the belongings of Lady Vertu?
Why are they covered with blood?
Is it because... Lady Vertu is having her menses?
I'm not...
Your Majesty, this maid is suspicious.
In my humble opinion, she should be
interrogated by the Department of Penalty.
Look what you've done with your dirty paws.
Take her out and flog her!
My Lady...
My Lady,
I was destroying evidence for you
but you would ruthlessly send me to death.
Why should I remain loyal to you?
Your Majesty... Your Majesty...
I dare not hide the truth from Your Majesty anymore.
Lady Vertu... is not pregnant at all.
Nor was I stealing these clothes.
A few days ago, Lady Vertu had her "monthly letters"
and stained her pants.
She asked me to throw them out.
These clothes are ironclad proof.
Aiya, Meizhuang...
Your Majesty... she is defiling my name.
Lady Vertu had a shock.
Send for the doctors.
Mr. Su,
please send for Dr. Liu,
who has been attending to my pregnancy.
I wonder if he's on shift tonight.
My Lady, Dr. Liu is not on duty tonight.
It's all right.
Send for the infirmary head, Zhang Mi.
Your Majesty, Dr. Liu has always been looking after my...
No matter!
Imperial doctors are the same.
Dr. Zhang, what is going on?
Was her prenatal qi affected?
I beg Your Majesties' forgiveness.
Lady Vertu...
she shows no fetal signs.
Nonsense!
I have a baby! How can I show no fetal signs?
Compose yourself, Meizhuang.
It might be a misdiagnosis.
I'm not a specialist in obstetrics.
I'd advise that we consult Dr. Jiang Cheng.
Send for him.
Your Majesty, Lady Vertu is not pregnant.
I wonder which doctor diagnosed her pregnancy.
That can't be true!
My Lady has been missing her menses, feels nauseous and craves sour food.
Aren't these pregnancy symptoms?
In my humble opinion, Lady Vertu
should have menstruated a few days ago.
However, her menstrual cycle has been delayed and irregular.
This should be the effect of certain medicines.
A few months ago, Lady Vertu asked me
for a prescription to delay her menstruation.
She hoped to adjust her menstrual cycle for a pregnancy.
Although I was hesitant, Lady Vertu said
she was doing it for the imperial family.
So I had to provide the prescription.
As to nausea and her liking for sour food,
I do not have any information.
Your Majesty, I did privately ask Dr. Jiang for a prescription.
But I wanted to prepare myself for
pregnancy, rather than delay menstruation.
Your Majesty, I've been wrongfully accused!
Show me the prescription.
We'll see the proof in black and white.
Lunar,
take out the prescription from the
bottom drawer of my dresser box.
Your Majesty,
I understand that private receipt of
prescriptions is an offense in the palace.
I beg for Your Majesty's pardon.
Indeed, but it is a minor offense
compared to feigning a pregnancy for favor.
My Lady, it's not there!
Don't bother!
- Su Peisheng.
- Your Majesty.
Bring Liu Ben here immediately.
He'll be tied up if he dares to hesitate.
Your Majesty, when Your Majesty summoned Dr. Jiang,
I sent for Dr. Liu as well.
But his residence... had already been vacated.
Very well then.
Lady Shen, he is from your hometown, isn't he?
It was you who recommended him to
attend to your pregnancy, was it not?
Your Majesty...
Anyone defending Shen will be convicted of the same offense.
Your Majesty, Lady Sourire has always been close to Lady Vertu.
I wonder if she was...
Silence!
May peace be restored in Your Majesty.
You deceived me and the Empress Dowager.
Don't you dare flaunt her hairpin!
[It was a disgrace for women to unfasten their hair publicly.]
Your Majesty, your health takes priority.
I have always appreciated your stable personality.
I would never expect you to
commit such an unspeakable crime:
trying to gain favor with a feigned pregnancy.
I am extremely disappointed.
Your Majesty, I've been wrongfully accused.
I truly have been wrongfully accused!
Your Majesty, I grew up with Meizhuang
and can vouch for her character.
If she has erred, I entreat Your Majesty to consider her
attentive service and offer her a chance to redeem herself.
I beg Your Majesty to reconsider.
I beg Your Majesty to forgive Lady Shen.
Lady Sourire is not wrong.
Lady Vertu was only too eager to have a child.
I hope Your Majesty will take account of her past service.
The Noble Lady surnamed Shen
has committed indecent acts.
She is to be demoted to Companion,
deprived of her honorary name
and confined to the Leisured Moon Chamber.
No one can visit her without my permission.
Your Majesty, please enlighten us
as for what to do about Liu Ben and Poria.
Capture Liu Ben, alive.
As for Poria,
death.
Meizhuang...
How could this happen?
How could this happen, Coua?
I'm so scared. Will this affect us?
Don't worry, at least Lady Sourire is still here.
Go quickly...
this...
burn this immediately!
You've been embroidering this for several days.
Are you sure you want to burn it, My Lady?
Anything related to her feigned pregnancy
will be taboo for His Majesty.
We would be in dire trouble if it were discovered.
Go, go quickly!
My work is done. Give me the money.
Of course.
Five thousand taels.
It should be enough for the rest of your life.
Count it before you go.
I'm afraid this will only last six months for me.
What? Liu Ben escaped?
Your Highness, quell your anger.
I've already sent people in pursuit.
Kill him immediately upon capture.
Liu Ben knows too much about us.
By no means is he to remain.
Yes.
Your Highness.
Rise.
I thank Your Highness.
Has Poria's family been taken care of?
Yes, Your Highness.
They have been amply rewarded and sent beyond Rehe Province.
Very well.
I made it clear to Poria that
her whole family would die if she failed.
But I promised her family a lifetime of wealth,
even if she had to die to succeed.
Your Highness is wise.
Poria has died a worthy death
to serve Your Highness and to protect her family.
You may leave.
Here he is.
Mr. Zhang!
Peace to Companion An.
Thank you, sir.
Mr. Zhang, you agreed yesterday to
bring My Lady's packages to her family.
We've brought the packages.
Thank you for your help, sir.
I'm truly sorry, Miss.
I'm afraid today I cannot fulfill the promise I made yesterday.
May I speak to you privately, sir?
Is 20 taels not enough for the trip?
If so, I will gather more for you, sir.
My Lady, in the course of one night,
Heaven and Earth have completely changed.
Lady Vertu is now Companion Shen.
I do not dare to send these packages for you.
Mr. Zhang! Mr. Zhang!
How can you go back on your word?
At least Lady Sourire is still there.
I'm not going back on my word.
Anyone associated with Companion Shen is taboo.
Why would I risk it?
As for Lady Sourire, she won't remain unscathed
when Companion Shen has fallen.
In my view, it won't be long: like "the tail of a rabbit".
All right, sir, tell me the truth.
What do I have to do
to have the packages delivered to my mother?
If I get to keep half the items.
Be careful. Go quickly.
This one, and that one. Hurry.
These are my palace's belongings.
Why are you taking them away?
Companion An, Her Highness said
that you entered here with Companion Shen.
According to your rank, you do not deserve
to live in such an ornate room.
But, by the grace of Her Highness,
you don't need to move to another residence.
As for the decorations here...
you have no use for them,
nor are you worthy of such possessions.
Her Highness instructed me to move all of them away.
And since these servants' quarters aren't well-decorated,
they can use yours!
(Eunuchs: Let's go.)
We've had an earful of Companion Shen.
(Song Zhi: Is everyone ready? Let's go.)
What did we gain when she was in favor?
Now that she's a Companion,
everyone not only tramples on her,
but kicks on us.
What kind of a world is this?
That's enough. Keep it to yourself.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Aiyo, you are still here, My Lady.
Please go.
The wars in the Northwest are tense.
His Majesty has spent all his time at court
and the Governance Hall for the past few days
reading memoranda or meeting ministers.
I'm afraid His Majesty doesn't have time to see you.
Thank you, Mr. Su. I will keep waiting for a while.
My Lady, I understand that you are anxious about Companion Shen.
But you must not neglect your own health.
My Lady, please use this.
Thank you very much, sir.
What a scorching day!
It was so much cooler inside.
Lady Sourire?
Why are you standing in the sun here?
Are you trying to rid yourself of
the mildew caused by your bad luck?
Peace and grace to Your Highness.
Of course I can have peace and grace
when the rats have been caught in the palace.
You may rise.
Isn't His Majesty busy with state affairs?
When is he not?
His Majesty is concerned about
my brother amidst the wars in the Northwest.
I just received a letter from my brother
and had to share every detail with His Majesty.
I thank Your Highness for the information.
I wonder if His Majesty is available at the moment.
His Majesty is with Lady Cao and Princess Wenyi.
Lady Sourire,
do you intend to go inside
and intercede for Shen Meizhuang?
His Majesty has been irked for several days.
Now that he can finally enjoy some quality time with Wenyi,
your intrusion will only remind His Majesty of Shen's
feigned pregnancy, whether you mention it or not.
Don't you think His Majesty will be more angry?
I trust that Meizhuang will never do such a thing.
Will His Majesty trust you, or the facts before his eyes?
Shen Meizhuang must have been blessed by her ancestors
to not have been executed already.
Being mockingly careless about the imperial lineage
will lead her to a lonely death in the palace.
Aiya, the sun is blazing.
- Song Zhi, we'll return.
- Yes.
Mr. Su, may I trouble you once more to
inform His Majesty of my request for an audience?
Your Majesty, Lady Sourire is still waiting outside to see you.
Your Majesty should let Lady Sourire in.
On such a hot day, when she's so worried about
Companion Shen, she might suffer heatstroke.
Companion Shen will also be distressed if Lady Sourire is unwell.
Then, Companion Shen won't be able to devote
herself to her self-reflection.
The lullaby you just sang is lovely.
You should sing it again to Wenyi.
Certainly.
(singing) Back and forth, my darling,
it's time to go to sleep.
My Lady,
His Majesty doesn't want to listen to you,
or think about Companion Shen.
My Lady, I'd suggest you return for now.
Thank you, sir.
My Lady, shall we go entreat the Empress to help us?
Meizhuang, think positively.
If you let the anger damage your health,
you will not be able to celebrate the day you become exonerated.
Thank you Estime, for coming to look after me.
You reside in my palace, but I failed to take good care of you
due to my inexperience with pregnancy.
Now, I am the only one permitted to visit you,
sometimes with just one foot in your door.
Lady Sourire is deeply concerned about you,
but she cannot get past all the guards outside.
Please tell her to protect herself,
and not offend His Majesty by speaking for me.
Meizhuang, anything I say to her
doesn't matter as much as you taking care of yourself.
Lady Sourire will have a difficult time if you become unwell.
All right... I'll eat something.
My Lady, stop peeling the lotus pod.
Your scallion-white fingernails have just grown out 2 lines [7 mm].
It would be a shame if you spoiled them.
I can't help feeling apprehensive now that it has come to this.
Concubine Estime does not have a heart of stone.
She will take care of things.
Meizhuang suddenly fell out of
"the burning favor that could sear a touching hand".
Even though His Majesty is lenient with her,
no one in the palace is easy to deal with.
How they must be trampling on Meizhuang!
Meizhuang is not one to swallow her pride.
What if she ...
My Lady.
If you'd like my advice, how about we turn to Madam Orchid?
She was your etiquette teacher,
and now she serves His Majesty directly.
Give this to her secretly.
Tell her I need her help to take care of Meizhuang.
Yes.
And give her a tube of Persian Brow Ink from my dresser.
Say it'll look good on her when working for His Majesty.
- My Lady...
- Just go.
The food is cold.
Shall I ask them to switch it for something warm?
It's all right. The Household Department
only has one meal sent to me daily.
Your chamber is heavily guarded.
Even I'm not able to bring anything in here.
Hold on.
Did you say your meals were sent here
by the Household Department?
Yes.
You can never be too careful in protecting yourself.
[Silver darkens when in contact with sulfur.]
It's poisoned!
What's going on?
Ah, nothing. The bowl slipped out of Companion Shen's hand.
You may leave.
My Lady.
My Lady, the Attendant Service has announced
that His Majesty will visit Consort Fleur tonight.
The closer His Majesty becomes to her,
the further he will turn from Meizhuang.
I'm afraid he is also suspicious of me now.
So he's been avoiding me all this time.
Maybe His Majesty is just busy with state affairs.
My Lady, His Majesty shares his pillow with you,
and he is especially intimate with you.
If His Majesty had wholehearted confidence in me, he would have
seen me immediately after announcing the punishment of Meizhuang.
He wouldn't ignore me or turn me away.
His Majesty not only shares his pillow with me,
but with others too.
I am no different from them.
Estime,
His Majesty is afraid that I might
tarnish the reputation of the imperial family.
So... so he needed my life to end.
No, that's not true, Meizhuang.
His Majesty is not a heartless person
and he would be heedful of your family's power.
If you died in my palace, they would say you
had committed suicide out of a guilty conscience.
And I would also be held accountable.
There is only one person who would
do such harm to you and me.
You mean... Consort Fleur!
I am not unaware of her ruthlessness.
How hard she fended me off, how much she hated me,
and how she tortured me with every tiny trick.
Estime, you must inform His Majesty!
But I... I'm afraid the words of my humble being
carry no weight before His Majesty.
If they intend to kill you,
they will make it appear like a guilty suicide.
Telling His Majesty would only
"beat the grass and startle the snakes".
But... what about my meals?
From now on, you must keep an eye out for tampering
in everything, not just your meals.
I will request for the Empress to allow
your meals to be made in my palace.
That would save trouble with the Imperial Kitchen.
Thank you for saving my life.
Please don't tell Huan'er about what happened today
in case she loses control of her patience.
To protect you is to protect myself.
I understand what to do as for Lady Sourire.
Your Majesty, the tea might still be hot.
You inked your eyebrows in the shape of "distant mountains".
Yes, I drew eyebrows for Empress Premièr in this style,
and that's how I remembered.
Oh.
[In Chinese ink painting, you only draw the ridges to depict distant mountains.]
Peace to Lady Sourire.
My Lady, His Majesty said he will come here tonight.
Please get ready.
- Thank you, sir.
- Allow me to take my leave.
His Majesty is finally going to see you, My Lady.
Will you find a chance to speak for Meizhuang?
At this juncture, I don't dare to even if I find a chance.
I'll have to wait until His Majesty's anger has passed.
Under such circumstances, it is reasonable to protect yourself.
I'll take every chance I can to help her.
These past few days, my mind was muddled with anger.
Cast your eye around the palace.
Each of them hoped that I would eagerly plead with His Majesty
and that the Emperor would punish me too.
I am not granting them their wish.
If only we had evidence to prove Meizhuang's innocence.
I know she must have been framed.
But without evidence in our hands,
I cannot pull even the cleverest tricks.
Right, Vermilion. Send Xiao-Yunzi to see
Dr. Wen Shichu at Duke Pei's residence.
Ask Dr. Wen to deliver my notes to my parents and
Meizhuang's grandparents in Beijing.
They have to find Liu Ben
whether dead or alive.
I don't believe a man could vanish without a trace.
I will see to that, My Lady.
Huang Guiquan is getting more competent at his job.
He even dared to send such flowers to my palace.
What a snobbish rat!
How dare he muddle with us
just because His Majesty hasn't been visiting!
I'll move the plant out of your sight, My Lady.
When even I am treated like this,
Meizhuang's situation must be unspeakable.
Before dawn, put the pomegranate flowers
in the most conspicuous place in the yard.
It will always remind me of today.
His Majesty hasn't arrived yet.
I'm afraid he probably won't visit.
Would you go to sleep now, My Lady?
It's all right.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
I'm exhausted.
Would Your Majesty like some sweet soup?
It was cooled with ice earlier, and not too cold by now.
It's better not to have icy food late at night.
I put some jasmine flowers in the chamber
so that Your Majesty will sleep soundly tonight.
You don't have anything else to tell me?
The sun blazes in the summer,
and gold hairpins can be dazzling to the eyes.
But those made of fishbone are hardly noticeable.
Si Lang, do you think I should use coral or black jade?
Was that your urgent problem?
Isn't it important for a girl to dress nicely
for the man who pleases her?
Certainly, of paramount importance.
In my view,
use coral.
Having a touch of red will brighten up your fair skin.
Thanks, Si Lang.
You are not going to speak for Shen?
"We can tell the strength of the horse from the number
of miles, and the heart of a person over the pass of days."
We'll find a trace if there is any left.
So why did you keep asking to see me?
You didn't see me for days, Si Lang.
Why am I not allowed to go to see you?
They all believed you were involved in Shen's case
because you're her closest friend.
Why do you not even say anything for yourself?
"A rumor spread three times is more dangerous than a tiger."
But Si Lang is a sagacious emperor,
and you know the person I am.
You wouldn't believe a one-sided story.
Si Lang, if you had any doubts in Huan Huan, you wouldn't
be here talking with me heart-to-heart, would you?
Why do you trust that I have no doubts in you?
You are the one I share my pillow with.
If I don't trust you, who can I possibly trust, or rely on?
You have made a decision about Meizhuang,
and I will not say anything about it.
And you already told me that I might have some troubles
after Consort Fleur regains her status.
I will not put you in a difficult position, Si Lang.
You've been very busy lately.
You should go to sleep, Si Lang.
Your Majesty, I heard that Huang Guiquan made a mistake
and was sent to the Department of Penalty this morning.
That's correct. He was too careless in even small tasks.
This morning when His Majesty came out of Lady Sourire's
residence, he was greeted by an array of withered flowers.
His Majesty got angry and sent him away.
I thought it was something more important.
Let him come back in a few days.
Every matter is important when serving the concubines.
He can be careless about yardwork today
and negligent in preparing the meals tomorrow,
or even turn his nose up at a concubine.
I understand he is a relative of yours,
and that is why we need to be strict with him over this matter.
You have a kind heart and don't see the consequences.
But an outsider may think he is abusing his power
relying on your influence.
That would not only hurt your reputation,
but also dismay His Majesty and distance him from you.
Not worth it.
I was just thinking that it would be difficult to find a replacement
at such short notice within the Household Department.
I didn't mean anything like that.
That is why we must disassociate you
from his wrongdoings to protect your prestige.
Of course, as for his replacement, I have promoted the
deputy head, Jiang Zhongmin, as the department head.
Your Majesty makes decision at lightning speed.
Your Majesty was saying that His Majesty
saw the flowers in Lady Sourire's yard.
But the Attendance Services recorded that His Majesty
selected Consort Fleur for last night.
How did His Majesty end up staying with Lady Sourire?
His Majesty might act on an impulse sometimes.
Certainly.
Had Consort Fleur been able to keep
His Majesty from visiting Lady Sourire,
Huang Guiquan would have been more fortunate.
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support or join us: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.